Perhaps we can discuss um how to spend
time in seclusion wisely
>> and more particularly
um how do you find out if you're acting
out of distraction?
>> Because distraction and entertainment
are not necessarily the same. It seems
to me distraction is a much wider
category. Movies, music, news can be on
the side of entertainment.
>> But it's not that if you refrain from
those things that you're automatically
not distracting yourself.
>> So how do people who come here for
example where there's little activity
going on outside of some work which is
really necessary or people who live by
themselves and have a fair amount of
time uh secluded from other people. um
um how to take advantage of those
circumstances, >> right?
>> right?
>> Well, the first step would obviously be
to abandon entertainment.
>> So, it is true that distraction is a
wider category than entertainment, but
you can be very sure that if you're
engaging with entertainment, you are
distracting yourself. There's no
question about that.
So to that extent you have accomplished
yourself in non-distraction. If you are
able to abandon those things and um not
depend on them anymore that is a better
position when it comes to u your
liability to distraction. Now
the problem is that then um that
category is so much wider than you that
you would have to realize that even
things that you think are wholesome
actually fall within distraction.
uh even though they're not against the
precepts because destruction is more
much more than just obvious activities
that you
you know at the level of external things
that you can either that you can just
stop and and just give it up. Your own
mind the momentum of your own mind
is by default going towards destruction.
So that's why when you would let's say
you've been properly established in the
precepts and sense restraint and then
you go into seclusion
what's going to feel easier
>> is to
spend all that time engaged in some kind
of mental activity.
study study.
>> Study. Yeah, you would. Or you might be
um rehearsing and bringing up ideas that
you um read about or heard about, which
is not a problem in itself, but we'll
get back to it. Or, you know, for some
people, they might spend time doing a
meditation technique, which is also a
distraction. um they might then um
um they might then um
or or if you're not making any effort at
all, you just spend time remembering
remembering things about the past
>> and planning for the future
uh or you know worrying about other what
other people think about you and what
happened today and what's going to
happen tomorrow.
>> So you will notice that it's not
something that you that you do because
you want it to happen necessarily.
you would realize that your mind has its
own its own momentum that prefers
distraction, prefers activity.
So that's the crucial thing to realize
because then you realize that it's it
won't be a matter of a simple decision
to just stop the distraction
>> as an
>> because that that could become your your
activity. That could become your thing
through which you overlook where your
mind actually is. that that kind of
constant um re reasserting. No, stop, stop, stop.
um re reasserting. No, stop, stop, stop.
And then that's why even when people
think that they're not thinking,
that doesn't at all mean that they're
inactive because you can be suppressing
your thoughts or you will be suppressing
your thoughts as an activity. And that's
what what that's what is distracting you
from being aware of what you actually
need to be aware of, which is your
motivation. Why am I trying to suppress
my thoughts for example? So the first
step then rather than trying to
blanket stop all activities is to start
becoming aware of the motivation behind
whatever activities remain once the
obviously unh wholesome activities have
been removed.
And then that you realize that will be a
much more subtle
um game, if you want to put it that way,
of almost like a cat and mouse game
where it it won't be necessarily
it it won't be necessarily
right in your face where the distraction
is, where the the mind is still kind of
leaning in these unh wholesome
directions, it won't be obvious.
But by emphasizing the motivation by by
asking yourself if if the mind is
thinking about X instead of
automatically seeing a problem with that
you ask yourself why is it thinking
about X? Is it passion? Is it obsessed
with something? Is it kind of um
is it clearly invested in things that
are not in in my control? And then if
you see that you see okay I will stop it
because of that not because the thought
in itself is a distraction
and then you know through that basically
you you won't see distraction as a thing
itself especially not in the beginning you have
especially not in the beginning you have
to approach it indirectly through like
these specific ways that it will
manifest. So you could say sensual
desire, aversion, laziness,
restlessness, doubt, the five
hindrances, those will be your
distraction. Th those will be the
pressures that will be taking you away
from recognizing
the presence of those very pressures.
So then that's where you would start
undoing it
as a as a as an indirect thing rather
than just as a choice to
not distract yourself. And then you
realize once you remove all these things
by not acting out of them, not by trying
to suppress them, then you will
automatically be non-distracted without
you trying to fabricate the
non-distraction as a thing that you do
because that will never work.
As long as you're putting your your
point of view and your point of and your
valition first, that's the thing that
will be distracting you. In other words,
it will be constricting the picture and
covering up the full scope of what's
happening internally.
>> Yeah. Just as boredom, for example, is
not something that we can volitionally
produce. You cannot say I'm going to do
this and that
>> and then I'm going to be bored. It will
arise naturally on account of
>> not doing a whole bunch of other things.
>> Y
>> but now if that starts to arise, can we
conclude that that's necessarily
wholesome? Can can we say that feeling
bored is okay or is there still some
sort of more subtle element of
resistance involved?
>> Yeah. Well, uh it can be a sign of
definitely if you were somebody who was
recently quite obviously giving into unh
quite obviously giving into unh
wholesome things.
>> Then boredom will be a symptom that you
are uh that you have ceased feeding
those unh wholesome things. So basically
it's it's only revealing you what's
already there. It's revealing you the
pressure and the momentum of mind that
you would have otherwise just continued
with. Mhm.
>> It's so then in in that instance it
would be quite important to recognize
it's not that the restraint
uh you know when when you said boredom
like that's exactly what would come up
when for example somebody who's been um
not restraining themselves from
entertainment even though they might
have been uh doing relatively well in
other regards
the boredom would still come up because
there is some minimal degree of activity
of of of kind of staying in touch with
the world that the mind that an
untrained mind would need to feel at
ease. So then cutting that off, it's not
that it would create that it's not that
it's creating the pain. It's not that
it's creating um
>> something that wasn't there before. It's
just revealing
the you could say infection or or
disease of the pressure that was already there
of the pressure that was already there
the whole time
>> and all these previous activities were
perhaps motivated by not wanting to feel
that that original quote unquote
disquire which was there the whole time.
>> Yeah.
>> So then then that's that's quite
important because then it would become
clear to you that you have no way no
escape from it. You're either acting out
of it, making it worse in the meantime,
or you are you stop acting out of it and
you you start doing something about it.
But you can't because it it almost feels
like when you distract yourself,
like you kind of like it's not there
anymore, the pressure of the boredom
feels like.
But the fact is
you realize immediately when you stop
distracting yourself, oh, it didn't go
away because otherwise, how could it get
worse? >> Yeah. That's the meaning of the
>> Yeah. That's the meaning of the
distraction. You were distracted from
it. So through distraction, you can
never resolve the original problem.
That's the whole point now.
>> Yeah. And then the more you train that,
the more you basically catch yourself
being already distracted because that's
how it's going to work. You won't be
able to kind of catch the first point.
Otherwise, you wouldn't have ended there
in the first place.
>> Um, then you start to realize actually
this promise of pleasure that comes from
distraction is actually just a trap.
It's it's not it's not really that
you're getting what you think you're
getting. In other words, you think that
you're resolving this internal pressure.
Actually, you're not. Which is why again
like you you take anybody who I don't
know was was pressured by boredom and
then they started watching a movie and
then the power goes out in the meantime.
>> Mhm.
>> You will see that the pressure will be
worse. >> Mhm.
>> Mhm.
>> Then you know if if the power had gone
out before
>> Yeah. or it turns out to be a really bad
movie. >> Yeah.
>> Yeah.
>> Because then because then indirectly
you'll be automatically reminded that
you were distracting yourself and that
intention is painful. It will bring you
back to like the pressure that you were
feeling the whole time.
>> Yeah.
>> So, so then if you become clear about
that, you realize well I I can't escape
from this.
>> I can either pretend that it's not there
and again keep making it worse
>> or I can endure this pain which is there
anyway but then you know going the way of
but then you know going the way of
restraint can gives you actually hope of
overcoming that pain. altogether
>> whereas the other way like you will have
the pain anyway but there's no chance
that you will ever overcome it by giving
into distraction. M
>> so then um that's that would be the
training as you said or as as we began
for somebody who has been established in
the other things because otherwise all
of this is just going to be abstract and
and it's not a it's not a coincidence
that when somebody hasn't developed
themselves in the precepts enough and in
sense restraint enough
they only feel like they have two
options when they're in seclusion.
either distract themsself with most
commonly with a meditation technique or
their mind is erasing left and right,
you know, completely out of control and
there's nothing in between precisely
because they haven't fulfilled these
more basic prerequisites that would
allow them to see the choice on of
distraction on the right level and just
refrain from that instead of trying to
overly determine
concentration for example to to like
just keep the mind from going there.
It's like you you don't have to uh I
know you don't you don't have to uh
play very loud music
in order for your shouts not to be
heard. You just have to stop shouting.
>> Uh stop loud music or no
>> play. You don't have to play loud music
so that other people don't hear you
shouting. You just have to stop
shouting. >> Yeah. Yeah.
>> Yeah. Yeah.
>> So in the same same sense you don't need
to like
>> uh resolve and and do focusing or do
some kind of mental activity that you
think is the practice in order to
prevent the unh wholesome things. It
just had to be aware of where the unh
wholesome things on the right level and
just not engage with it.
>> Okay. Yeah. I mean, it just seemed like
uh the the way you said it that shouting
is like a a choice
>> as opposed to like a
>> But is it because I thought shouting is
you tackle the shouting indirectly or
maybe I actually didn't.
>> No, no, it's like it's it's
>> Well, maybe Yeah, it's worth clarifying.
It's not that you can stop the momentum
of the mind's pressure as a choice the
same way you can stop the shouting.
>> Yeah.
>> But either way, it's the same cuz you
know, you might have the pressure to
keep shouting.
>> I understood. So the the technique is
the shouting. Yeah.
>> Which you can clearly Yeah. Yeah.
>> Or or that or might be, you know, for
some people it might just be like overly
clarifying and revolving around ideas
that you if you kind of stop and ask
yourself, oh, is this actually purifying
my mind
>> from an wholesome states
>> the way that this is to say reflection
should like right reflection should? You
realize it's not. it's very often making
it worse, winding me up with more doubt
and more pressure, which means this
can't be what the Buddha meant with, you
know, reflecting on the dharma that
you've heard as a thing that would
purify you actually from unh wholesome
states. So that's something I I
mentioned before. It's um you you you'll
have to learn the line also because
that's one thing that
would be part of the solution like
reflecting, contemplating, reminding
yourself of the right themes
>> would be a way to lean your mind away
from this default tendency to distract
itself. Like reflect on the danger of
this, reflect on what all all what we
just said. Like the pain is there
anyway. it's not actually being
resolved. You know, keep reminding
yourself of that every time you feel the
the pressure to distract yourself and
that is going to contribute to your
ability to not give into it. But then
the the the
difficulty is like you will have to be
aware again as I said before your
intention >> because if you are clear okay I am
>> because if you are clear okay I am
contemplating the dharma because I see
my mind leaning in this direction and
I'm trying to rein it back in
>> that's a wholesome reason to contemplate
but then at other times you realize no
no what the mind wants is the
clarification is the thinking is the uh
revolving around these ideas and then
that becomes your distraction.
>> Yeah. Or Yeah.
>> Depending on the motivation behind it.
>> Yeah. Could be acting out of the
hindness of doubt for example.
>> So then I mean that applies to
everything but this is a a case that
quite illustrates it quite well. How
wholesome and unh wholesome is not about
the things. It's about why are you doing
it at that time.
>> Mh. So then contemplation is is a
perfect example because even the sutras
talk about it and it is it is the way
that you would even develop Janna in
many of the sutras it's described and
yet if you do it wrongly i.e. if you do
it with the wrong motivation it will be
precisely what would be keeping you
keeping your mind defiled. It would be
the gateway for your acting out.
>> Yes. But now um so to clear up whether
there's a difference between motivation
and intention can we say that intention
is most generally greed hatred delusion
and delusion right or let's say five
hindrances >> because I could be motivated to become
>> because I could be motivated to become
enlighten
>> and and then start using that motivation
to justify all sorts of things but that
should be refined because that's never
going to happen as long as they're still
acting out of
>> of an an awesome own states.
>> Yeah. But but the motivation would be I
I guess it's just semantics. But uh when
I say motivation, I don't mean like a
rational explanation that you give.
>> Exactly.
>> That I'm I'm thinking about the dharma
because the Buddha said this is good or
some kind of
>> welfare other people's welfare. So it's
therefore always right.
>> It's not about you. It's about
motivation. Is about
what is making this feel pleasant right
now. what is making this feel appealing
right now?
>> What is it?
And then you'll get to see it's either
yeah like you said greed aversion or
delusion or uh it could be uh wisdom
>> and clarity about what actually needs to
be done. So then ask yourself why is
this direction of contemplation
appealing >> right now? Is it because I I am clear
>> right now? Is it because I I am clear
that this will help me steer my mind
away from an wholesome state or or
increase the wholesome states that are
already there.
>> Or is it because it's appealing as a way
of like scratching the itch?
>> Yeah. So appealing cannot be equated
with pleasure. No.
>> Because to steer away could be very well
unpleasant. But then the wisdom which is
the appealing bit has to supersede that.
>> Yeah. Yeah. So then you you same as you
rec as you would
>> have like a unpleasant uh pill or or
>> medicine
>> or or concoction that you have to drink
and it tastes very bitter
>> but it's appealing because you are
>> quite sure and aware of the fact that
this will cure you from the much more
unpleasant >> illness that you're experiencing. So in
>> illness that you're experiencing. So in
that sense
>> it is obviously a very different type of
uh appeal
>> but uh initially you won't necessarily
see the difference. So you have to ask
yourself why that why do I want to do
this now whatever it is
>> but you know it applies even to this
case as well and it's important to know
that it applies to this case as well
because you know that's how initially
you would come to the practice
inevitably by thinking about these
things reflecting on them and you know
that's how you learn that's how you get
the information that's how you clarify
what needs to be
But then if you never question your
motivations for thinking and reflection
doesn't mean you need to stop it as I
said it means you question your
motivation behind it then you will be
limited in how far you will go
>> in discerning wholesome and unh
wholesome >> and I think even just if uh you want to
>> and I think even just if uh you want to
uh I guess I would be curious to ask
what would be your definition of wisdom
right because I you just asked
Um what would be the difference between
that motivation that sort of pushing to
get enlightened
as opposed to rightly reflecting
on what wisdom itself is
and then kind of finding your way
indirectly to what that is. So I guess
my question would be is like what would
you define as wisdom?
Well, wisdom would have to be
basically the clarity that supersedes
even the the attempts of the mind to
take take you in the opposite direction.
Because wisdom like sometimes you will
feel inspired. For example,
sometimes you have the
the push and the the inclination
to be restrained to cultivate
renunciation and all these things. But
none of that is necessarily wisdom
because you you you can that that will
come and go. Wisdom is when even despite
the pressure trying to take you in the
opposite direction, you're still fully
clear. This is where I need to go. So
wisdom is when it it is able to survive
the winds of the defamments.
I actually had a follow up on it, but if
you if you wanted it might lead down
kind of a bit of a tangent to what you
were talking about. So I can also
>> wait if you had more to ask on on this
topic. >> No, there's no particular agenda. So we
>> No, there's no particular agenda. So we
can just we can just explore also what
is wisdom like uh because as you just
mentioned like can you actually start
from the beginning reflecting on wisdom
>> or is that by definition going to be
problematic >> because um there might very well not be
>> because um there might very well not be
let's say any wisdom to begin with. Uh
so you so you would have to start by
taking on faith the the the right
instructions which will go against quite
deeply rooted intuition. And so from the
going back to the starting point, I
would I would emphasize that because
otherwise you run the risk that you
think that you are contemplating wisdom
which has got nothing to do with the
wisdom. >> Right. What Yeah. Now now just said you
>> Right. What Yeah. Now now just said you
mentioned intuition.
That's another way of basically you
often times wisdom is felt as if it's
like this either you have
you have wisdom or you don't
>> a pleasant feeling. I mean I mean that's
that's how I would say a lot of people
think wisdom is a pleasant feeling. It's
like oh I figured it out. No, but but
sorry that's that's
>> I mean it can't feel that way
>> but
>> what you need to be aware of is what I
said just before like when it feels
appealing to go in these direction. I
mean the the the wrong wisdom just just
to be clear. Not not the right wisdom.
But then when it feels appealing to go
in a certain direction when certain
ideas feel like they make a lot of
sense. >> If that's because you're inspired
>> If that's because you're inspired
>> and then when that inspiration goes away
then it doesn't make sense anymore. It
doesn't kind of feel right anymore.
That's when it's not wisdom. That's when
it's just
>> Yeah. Exactly.
>> circumstantial inspiration. I think
that's what so the the question I guess
I was trying to ask was that um yeah you
know wisdom at least the way I would
define it is seeing well seeing what you
thought how do I say it essentially like the
how do I say it essentially like the
scaffolding there's something that was
already always there in your experience
that you just didn't recognize it as
such >> and seeing that there
>> and seeing that there
>> as something that you did not question.
>> Mhm.
>> And therefore you can unbburden yourself
with it.
>> Mhm.
>> That's how that's what I would define as
wisdom. And
naturally the way one gets to that
uh well yeah initially you have to take
take on effort. So you take on the
precept, you take on sense training, you
do these things. But once you're
sufficiently established in it, you have
to sort of um
>> undo.
>> Yeah, exactly. Like sort of Yeah. I
mean, like these days I sort of I kind
of really see it as more like I don't
know like more more physics as opposed
to like
designations, right? like you sort of
>> like you you sort of feel that you're
pushing forward and like the Buddha
said, I I cross the shore by neither
pushing forward nor standing still. And
it's about like you just find yourself a
little bit too forward than you need to
be
>> to then kind of uh
>> uncover that wisdom.
>> Yeah. So to speak.
>> So bas Well, no. Wisdom would be what
would allow you to to recognize when
you're going the wrong direction.
>> Oh, okay. But then what would you call
the moment? Let's say that you recognize
something that wasn't questioned. So you
know you're sufficiently established
there isn't an a pressure
>> there. Now you decide to contemplate
something that you haven't contemplated
for a while.
>> You're like, "Oh crap, that's that's
something I took for granted."
>> What would you call that?
Well, the thing that would the wisdom
would be the thing that would guide you
to recognize those things in the first
place. It's not that they come
spontaneously. >> No, of course. I mean, you like I said,
>> No, of course. I mean, you like I said,
once the ground is fertile, so to speak.
>> Mhm.
>> Well, that ground being fertile is what
the wisdom is.
>> That's what you would call wisdom. Not
like the specific instances of
recognizing things cuz anybody can have
instances like and then later on they
would through bad choices and bad habits
they would lose the clarity that they
had before. And you would see that many
times like somebody might even write you
an essay
>> that you know sounds like they
>> they were going the right direction
which means like oh yeah they were
coming up with these right ideas
>> but then because that ground the actual
ground was not fully fertile. Eventually
they fall from whatever it is that they
inspiration might have been one of them
or you know whatever was was getting
them to keep the precepts and and
maintain that ground
>> they fall from it and then
even those ideas that they had before
that felt like oh I should explore this
and this is
>> that and it and might have even brought
a sense of clarity and release
>> it doesn't anymore
>> right but uh Um what would you call the
designation for someone who is
>> yeah like is is is or is it not even
worth emphasizing in any way that kind
of um yeah I mean again like I'm saying
it's you sort of at some point you need
to start once you're established I would
assume you need to start seeing things
at a more sub subtle subtle level
>> but wait but what do you mean by
established like established in what
>> precepts and sense restraint.
>> Yes.
>> So first of all perhaps you should
emphasize when you talk about fertile
ground >> this means that without virtue and
>> this means that without virtue and
restraint there's not going to be any
wisdom. >> Mhm.
>> Mhm.
>> Yeah. That's the first thing right?
>> So when you say being established I
presume you mean establish in that.
>> Yes. Yeah. Exactly. Good.
>> So now someone is established in that
and you're now trying to find out where
does the wisdom come in? Does it
automatically follow from the virtue and
the restraint?
Like do virtue and restraint
automatically reveal to you those things
that were already there? Because that's
what you were touching upon earlier.
>> Yeah, exactly. But I think I'm I'm
asking kind of a
>> because we already got a definition of
wisdom. >> Mhm.
>> Mhm.
>> Which is that the recognition of your
situ where you are in your situation,
>> right? Would that be fair to say fair to
someone? >> Depends what you mean situation. You
>> Depends what you mean situation. You
could basically say wisdom is when
you're able to recognize the the
important wisdom is when you're able to
recognize the state of your mind,
>> right?
>> Mind affected with passion,
>> mind not affected with passion, mind
affected with a version, mind not
affected with
>> because that's what lasts. That's what
can't be taken away. Even if you I mean
sure you can be
>> even exactly even if the mind then you
know the when the mind is not passionate
when the mind is not averse
>> things can be clear because of that
because the kind of
>> the clouds are not there anymore
>> and naturally you would have more
clarity but if the cloud clouds come
back >> you lose the clarity which means
>> you lose the clarity which means
>> which it wasn't wisdom to be
>> exactly
>> yeah so
>> we we're here and I again maybe it's a
too technical of a
But I was just curious what would you
call the designation
once you have developed that fertile
ground and now you decide whatever
contemplate space
>> the phenomena of space.
>> Mhm.
>> And you recognize stuff that was already
there. >> Mhm.
>> Mhm.
>> That you didn't necessarily see through
the lens of space
and it's like a aha moment. Let's say
what would you if that's not wisdom cuz
I mean obviously that no that's I
definitely wouldn't call that wisdom
because >> well you could you could call it insight
>> well you could you could call it insight
>> because see well if you could call it
wisdom >> you know the more
>> you know the more
on our hand is somebody who has fully
developed wisdom
>> and they would be completely free from
aha moments because there's nothing that
they haven't understood
>> exactly.
>> So then you couldn't associate that with
wi with wisdom because you know it would
be actually inversely proportional. the
more wisdom you had, the less you would
realize that you didn't.
>> Sure. Okay. I mean, like, yeah. So,
maybe what I meant
is that
so the aha m you don't you don't Yeah.
You you don't want to go down the road
of like the more aha moments I'm having,
>> the better it is. Not necessarily.
Um but that aha moment does does lead to
more dispassion because
something that you were well inherently
overlooking >> Mhm.
>> Mhm.
>> and had some sense of burden
>> is seen as something that's not yours as
there as was there from the beginning.
>> So that's what that aha moment would
lead you down as dispassion. It's not
something you can own. But if you
qualify it like that because there might
also be people practicing all sorts of
focusing methods and techniques which
can give rise to all sorts of aha
moments that do then not necessarily
lead to the discussion.
>> Yeah. But but still the wisdom would be
more on the level of that even when that
happens when when you
when when you
>> get you recognize things that you didn't
see before
>> you don't be compassionate to that.
>> Yeah. Sure. Yeah. So that is the only
wisdom that you would have to be
concerned about because
>> as the Buddha even said knowledge and
vision the holy life is not lived for the sake
the holy life is not lived for the sake
of knowledge and vision.
There's that also where he talks about
the hardwood. Then he says some people
developing samadei they would achieve
knowledge and vision and then they would
become satisfied with that. Then he says
even that is not the goal of the
practice. So the goal is not even to understand
So the goal is not even to understand
the quote unquote right things. He said
the word the goal is extinguishment
through non assumption or non clinging.
>> Okay.
>> So then even when somebody would get the
right insights quote unquote
>> the actual nibbana is whether they're
able to remain dispassionate in regard
to that.
>> Yes. So that means that if somebody gets
Alzheimer and doesn't remember any of
their aha moments anymore doesn't mean
that their wisdom is gone.
>> Exactly.
>> Which also raises the question is the
wisdom on the side of you or is the
wisdom on the side of cha understanding
things for itself now
>> because that is also how you can
distinguish between uh what what you
mentioned earlier like neither leaning
forward nor standing still and so on.
Yeah. that because those would be
attitudes that you would have in
relation to taming or training the mind.
>> But can we also say that when the mind
actually sees rightly for itself how to
not suffer that that is where wisdom
begins that that the wisdom in a sense
has nothing to do with you.
>> Yeah. But but uh even before we go that
route >> I just realized so what you just said
>> I just realized so what you just said
you could basically just say those are
damas those are images that arise. Oh,
regarding what's
>> when something becomes clear when
something that you were overlooking
before it becomes clear
>> that happens as a
>> that is one of the symptoms of the
obstructions being removed
>> or being lessened at least.
>> Mhm.
>> But that in of itself is just an image.
>> No, the actual wisdom and dispassion
would be in relation to that.
>> Exactly. So the way the way I would uh
sort of continue with what would happen
is like you would have this aha moment
and what that should reveal to you is
ironically more pressure. Like
>> you sort of need to let the dust settle.
So you have an aha moment. It's like oh
I didn't look in this direction.
>> Mhm.
>> And I was carrying holding on to all
this stuff
>> and now you need to like continue that
sense of restraint. But now you have a
tune that was kind of invisible to you
if if that makes sense.
>> Right. But then I mean if if if it is
happening on the right level that you're
becoming aware of your passion in regard
to things
>> then yeah you could say those are
moments where you're
>> you can
reasonably assume that your wisdom is has been
assume that your wisdom is has been
developing. But it's not that the wisdom
is those has anything that again the
more wisdom you had the less the more
impossible it would be for you to
overlook anything the more impossible it
would be for there to feel like there's
anything new or anything unexplored. So
>> right
>> the wisdom would be
the perpetual clarity
>> that prevents you from holding on to
things in the first place.
>> Yeah.
And that the the that type of wisdom
has to be permanent.
>> It cannot be something that comes and
goes. >> For sure. And I mean, as long as you
>> For sure. And I mean, as long as you
still suffer, you still know that you
need more more wisdom.
>> Yeah. So, you wouldn't measure it at all
by
um anything that
that just happens in in a specific
moment. Wisdom is an irreversible
>> at least well from the point of right
view onwards wisdom is irreversible.
>> But then let me ask it this way. Is
there a way to wisdom without some level
of aha moments?
>> No.
>> Okay.
>> But even then the aha moments have again
to be
>> have to come second. Well yeah they have
to come second to the actual dispassion.
>> Yeah. And and the aha moments,
the what the aha is about should always
be, oh, I was passionate in regard to
this and I didn't realize it.
>> Yeah. Yeah. Exactly. Yeah. Yeah.
>> Never like like that. Some new thing
>> pops up and then you Yeah. You figure
something out,
>> right? Yeah.
>> I mean, so then technically aha moment
is only really worth it if it allows you
to become further dispassionate towards
stuff that you didn't realize you were
passionate towards. Well, no. I mean,
even more accurately, if the aha moment
is about this passion,
if you become aware of like, oh, I was
overlooking my passion in regard to
this. Now, I'm not overlooking it
anymore. >> Uh, right. But, uh,
>> Uh, right. But, uh,
does so you're saying it doesn't
necessarily need to have like a dust
settling time if you understand what I
mean by that. like you know you can have
like a like a just maybe describe a
situation you have a neutral feeling
that there's no really pressure to go
anywhere >> and now you decide to like well let me
>> and now you decide to like well let me
like see what else is there and then
you'll see you'll have an aha moment and
that aha moment now reveals to you a
bunch of pressure that that was there
>> does that necessarily need to be the
case um if if you follow me Uh yeah. Well,
um if if you follow me Uh yeah. Well,
like
even those kind of revelations would be
temporary, would be ephemeral because if
you >> say well of I mean temporary in in a
>> say well of I mean temporary in in a
good way because
I mean that stuff you don't want in your
experience anyway.
>> Yeah. But like all those realizations
would be basically what anybody even
without right view they would be they
would be realizing like that's how you
would purify your mind from the five
hindrances. But then as that suta says
if somebody would think that oh because
they've uh they've been able to purify
these things that these things will
never come back it would be the same as
saying like when it rains and the dust
settles on the on the road that oh this
this dust will never come back. So those
are the things that developments that
you would have through the graduate
training that like you start recognizing
oh yeah there's this pressure that I've
been overlooking.
you don't overlook it anymore. Like
that's exactly how you would develop
samadei even without the right view.
>> But then the actual right view is not
about that. The actual right view is
independent of all those aha moments and
that kind of perspective that expands
and contracts
>> over time. It's completely independent.
Has nothing to do with
>> Yeah. Yeah. And I guess that's why I
hope we using the designation aha as
opposed to anything more specific
because if it becomes anything more
specific that you've figured out space
and now you don't you don't need to
worry about space ever again.
>> Yeah. No, but even even then it like if
if it's a realization of oh I was acting
out of sensual desire. I was acting out
of aversion. All that is just the five
hindrances. So anybody would have that.
It doesn't have anything explicitly to
do with the right view. is the basis for
the right view
to to recognize you know your own acting
out of hindrances because that's the
only way you can overcome them
and yeah it's not about like the thing
about space and all that that's like not
even that's nothing
>> yeah got
>> so then um
so the see the aha moments even that
would is not necessarily part of the
Buddhist teaching like it's it's when
>> independently of the state of your mind
independently of what has moved, what
has changed, what has come up, what has
gone away. You realize am I like full on
on the most fundamental level. Am I
passionate? Am I dispassionate?
>> Yeah, I mean I I I would agree with that
statement of of course the one could say
that actual sort of party is like the it
would also be an aha moment of sorts,
right? To kind of well see that there's no
To kind of well see that there's no
outside of this. Well, no. Even that
would be part of just developing somati.
Like you you cannot be your mind cannot
be composed if you still conceive of an
outside. That's a that's a whole
definition of the mind being scattered
>> of onepointedness
which is the opposite of focusing on one
particular thing in the midst of other
things. You go in the opposite
direction. So you have this
>> this this wholeness totality. Let's put
like that. So that's why that's exactly
why samadei would be the basis for
developing the right view
>> because then it it it becomes clear that
there is no outside. So then what would
you Okay. So if I understand you
correctly then
so if uh the aha moments aren't part of
the Buddhist teaching what would you
then describe the right the right view
as? M well so that any phenomenon no
matter how subtle it is
>> can kind of excite you to the point
where you overlook your attitude in
regard to it
>> and you wouldn't arrive at that
>> through aha moments. No,
>> it would be
>> you you wouldn't
>> you wouldn't arrive at that through a
moment because the aha moments will be
things that excite you in such a way
that you overlook your attitude in
regard to them. Like that's all these
all these uh aesthetics that would in
the in the Buddhist teaching would say
like you know developing the the
perception of of
uh
the the base of neither perception nor
non-perception the base of nothingness
that would be like oh wow there is this
whole plane
>> of existence basically that you were
completely unaware of all these
defilements that were holding you back
from being established in this domain
like passion doors is a lower domain.
Same as with the five hindrances, you
you kind of catch yourself leaning
towards some sensual object and you it
felt like it was completely automatic,
completely moving on its own momentum
and you realize, oh, wait, I'm actually
doing this. This is optional. I don't
have to continue this momentum. And then
you don't give into that. That's that's
a basic realization that um that is what
samadei is basically. So it's that's why
and that's why it says there is no
samari for somebody who
like you cannot separate seeing through
things as it as it's called vibasa
as it as it's called vibasa
>> and uh samata
>> sam
>> because you will be recognizing things
if you're actually if your mind is
actually getting composed
>> I see
>> but then
>> in the Buddhist teaching yeah how does
the Buddhist teaching fit into this
>> in the Buddhist teaching it's like
>> well
in regards to all of that in regard to
any phenomena high or low
>> inferior spe or sublime
>> that it's still you don't overlook the
fact that you are passionate in regard
to it or not. So that's why there was
that suta where well the first suta in
the majikaya where the Buddha says
somebody conceives nibbana
>> conceives in nibbana conceives from
nibbana takes like says nibbana is mind he
takes like says nibbana is mind he
delights in it and it's because you know
it might be uh let's say aha moment to
continue using that designation of like
virtually the right direction of where
this passion is But because they
overlook that they are passionate in
regard to this discovery quote unquote
>> because of that it's not
>> so then yeah and I guess the post-wright
view could you then just kind of develop
more or less the same practice that the
people who attained either perception or
no perception that you know the practice
that would lead them to that so anything
that kind of
>> gets delivery
>> yeah it's a delivery
>> I'll go yeah
Well, from here looks like the guy drove
off. >> Yeah.
>> Yeah.
>> So, you were saying whether after the
right view
>> Yeah. After the right,
>> somebody would be able to still develop
those same things. Well, yes, but it
would be completely different in its
nature because then the whole thing is
coming through the angle of the right
dispassion. I see. And there are no kind
of blind spots in regard to it. Which is
why it would take very little
for like it would be automatic really
that somebody who actually has the right
view if they were to develop these
things they would automatically become
an ara
>> they wouldn't have to go through like
questioning oh what where is my blind
spot in regard to this it would be
obvious because
>> they have understood
>> that principle like well it doesn't
matter how high low how how subtle how
kind of enlightening it is it doesn't
matter what matter what matters is what
is my attitude in regard to it and then
that that cannot become forgotten no
matter how far they travel in the
direction of Janas and Samari and all
this >> and actually can I so just to sort of
>> and actually can I so just to sort of
cuz I can't really
understand you know like how it like how
this works
>> you know yeah like it because you you
have these designations right
>> Mhm. that if you're at at neither
perception nor neither perception nor
non-perception, >> uh obviously you're not holding on to
>> uh obviously you're not holding on to
the to the designation of the practice
that got you there cuz it would it seems
rather >> you may not even know about it. No.
>> you may not even know about it. No.
>> So
you're holding on to isn't even at the
level of designations.
>> Well, designations are not like the
labels that you speak about.
Designations are much more
>> subtle. I I see. Okay. So but it's just
kind of they've but how have they gone
to that direction?
>> Well by that's actually
one thing that that's important to
understand all these names that you read
in the sutas those are names that you
know that are developed so that you can
talk about these things but somebody who
is training themselves they wouldn't
even need to know about these names.
That's why you have that suta where like
um a monk is established in I don't know
the first Janna and then he asks okay so
is there further than this and then
without it being told in advance that
there is the second Janna they continues
striving and they arrive at the second
one >> I see
>> I see
>> but they may not even have the name
>> so it could even just be complacency
that they've reached that plane of
either perception or no perception
>> and they just
>> Oh no it's not that it's It's not that
like you know they knew that you have
all of these eight and you decide to
like oh I just stay here.
>> No, it's it's like
>> you have developed
>> precisely what you said like you see
yourself. That is the only way that you
would develop these things. It's like
you see your defilements, you notice
them, you abandon them, you're able to
to move to move on to the next. It's you
cannot develop it through like doing
something else that completely overlooks
the place where the pressures are. It
has to be developed through
abandoning the five hindrances. That is
the only way that you can achieve any of
these states. So that's why it's not a
huge jump when these people were
thinking that they were arro. It's not
that they were like super uh far off the
mark and they were just kind of um
almost like a cartoonish
uh conceited just blind nonsense. No, it
was like they have actually been working
on that right level of noticing greed
aversion and delusion not acting out of
it until it actually fact actually goes
away. And the result of that is the mind
ascending on into these more subtle and
subtle planes. So uh yes with the right
view you have to develop these things
but it would come from a completely
different place. you wouldn't be able to
develop any kind of um
how how would you call it like
uh yeah losing perspective uh making
something special out of them
>> becoming kind of um dependent on them
overlooking that well
>> no matter how how lofty and and uh no
matter how even
like those planes are more, you could
even say they're more fundamental than
the other stuff, the normal state of
being that you live in. Even then, you
wouldn't be able to become dependent on
those and overlook that. Wait, wait,
wait a second. It doesn't matter in
which of these my mind is.
>> That is not what the point of this whole
training is. The point is
>> that other perpendicular dimension of
like what is my attitude in regard to
this So in a way it's the same it's the same
So in a way it's the same it's the same
thing that you would have used to
develop samadei.
>> It's like asking yourself where your
motivations are and all that stuff.
purification. >> But then you know whether you apply it
>> But then you know whether you apply it
then to the result of that practice or
not that's a different question and most
people don't because it feels without a
Buddha you wouldn't because it feels
like this is it like it's it's it's been
purified from everything and then
>> only from the outside somebody from the
outside tells you like wait no
>> this is not quite it because when when
you're talking about it and you're
saying oh their attitude in regard to
it. It sounds like this obvious thing
like that only a fool would overlook.
But no,